Chapter 1
Getting Started
This chapter is about getting started with Git. We will begin at the beginning by explaining some background on
version control tools, then move on to how to get Git running on your system and finally how to get it set up to start
working with. At the end of this chapter you should understand why Git is around, why you should use it, and you
should be all set up to do so.
About Version Control
What is “version control,” and why should you care? Version control is a system that records changes to a file or set of
files over time so that you can recall specific versions later. For the examples in this book you will use software source
code as the files being version controlled, though in reality you can do this with nearly any type of file on a computer.
If you are a graphic or web designer and want to keep every version of an image or layout (which you would most
certainly want to), a Version Control System (VCS) is a very wise thing to use. It allows you to revert files to a previous
state, revert the entire project to a previous state, compare changes over time, see who last modified something that
might be causing a problem, who introduced an issue and when, and more. Using a VCS also generally means that if
you screw things up or lose files, you can easily recover. In addition, you get all this for very little overhead.
Local Version Control Systems
Many people’s version-control method of choice is to copy files into another directory (perhaps a time-stamped
directory, if they’re clever). This approach is very common because it is so simple, but it is also incredibly error
prone. It is easy to forget which directory you’re in and accidentally write to the wrong file or copy over files you
don’t mean to.
To deal with this issue, programmers long ago developed local VCSs that had a simple database that kept all the
changes to files under revision control.
Chapter 1 ■ Getting Started
2
One of the more popular VCS tools was a system called RCS, which is still distributed with many computers
today. Even the popular Mac OS X operating system includes the rcs command when you install the Developer Tools.
RCS works by keeping patch sets (that is, the differences between files) in a special format on disk; it can then
re-create what any file looked like at any point in time by adding up all the patches.
Figure 1-1. Local version control
Chapter 1 ■ Getting Started
3
Centralized Version Control Systems
The next major issue that people encounter is that they need to collaborate with developers on other systems. To
deal with this problem, Centralized Version Control Systems (CVCSs) were developed. These systems, such as CVS,
Subversion, and Perforce, have a single server that contains all the versioned files, and a number of clients that check
out files from that central place. For many years, this has been the standard for version control.
Figure 1-2. Centralized version control
This setup offers many advantages, especially over local VCSs. For example, everyone knows to a certain degree
what everyone else on the project is doing. Administrators have fine-grained control over who can do what; and it’s far
easier to administer a CVCS than it is to deal with local databases on every client.
However, this setup also has some serious downsides. The most obvious is the single point of failure that the
centralized server represents. If that server goes down for an hour, then during that hour nobody can collaborate
at all or save versioned changes to anything they’re working on. If the hard disk the central database is on becomes
corrupted, and proper backups haven’t been kept, you lose absolutely everything—the entire history of the project
except whatever single snapshots people happen to have on their local machines. Local VCS systems suffer from this
same problem—whenever you have the entire history of the project in a single place, you risk losing everything.
Chapter 1 ■ Getting Started
4